This is your conference,
هذا هو مؤتمركم،
and I think you have a right to know a little bit right now, in this transition period,
أعتقد أن لديكم الحق لمعرفة القليل الآن، في هذه الفترة الإنتقالية،
about this guy who's going to be looking after it for you for a bit.
حول هذا الشخص الذي سيكون مسئولاً عنه لفترة.
So, I'm just going to grab a chair here.
اذا، سأقوم بتقريب الكرسي هنا.
Two years ago at TED, I think --
قبل عامين في تيد، أعتقد--
I've come to this conclusion --
توصلت لهذه الخلاصة--
I think I may have been suffering from a strange delusion.
أعتقد أنني ربما كنت أعاني من حالة غريبة من الوهم.
I think that I may have believed unconsciously,
أعتقد أنني ربما أعتقدت بلا إدراك
then, that I was kind of a business hero.
حينها أنني نوعا ما بطلاً للأعمال.
I had this company that I'd spent 15 years building. It's called Future;
لديّ هذه الشركة التي قضيت 15 عاماً في بنائها، كان أسمها المستقبل.
it was a magazine publishing company.
كانت شركة لنشر المجلات.
It had recently gone public
و قد طرحت شركة للإكتتاب العام مؤخراً،
and the market said that it was apparently worth two billion dollars,
ويقال أن قيمتها السوقية تساوي بليوني دولار،
a number I didn't really understand.
وهو رقم لا أستطيع فهمه.
A magazine I'd recently launched called Business 2.0
مجلة أخرى أطلقتها قريباً تسمى أعمال 2.0
was fatter than a telephone directory,
كان أكبر من فهرس الهاتف،
busy pumping hot air into the bubble.
مشغول بضخ الهواء السخن داخل الفقاعة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I was the 40 percent owner of a dotcom
-- وكنت مالكاً ل 40 في المائة من شركة دوت كوم
that was about to go public and no doubt be worth billions more.
التي كانت على وشك أن تصبح إكتتاب عام ولا شك تساوي بلايين أكثر.
And all this had come from nothing.
وكل هذا جاء من لا شئ.
Fifteen years earlier, I was a science journalist who people just laughed at
قبل 15 عاماً، كنت صحفي علوم يضحك عليه الناس
when I said, "I really would like to start my own computer magazine."
عندما قلت، " أريد بالفعل بدء مجلة الكمبيوتر خاصتي."
And 15 years later, there are 100 of them
وبعد 15 سنة هناك-- هناك 100 مجلة.
and 2,000 people on staff and it was just such heady times.
و 2,000 شخص في فريق العمل-- كانت أوقات عنيدة.
The date was February 2000.
التاريخ كان فبراير عام 2000.
I thought the little graph of my business life
أعتقدت أن الرسم البياني لحياتي العملية
that kind of looked a bit like Moore's Law --
يبدو مثل ما عليه قانون موري--
ever upward and to the right -- it was going to go on forever.
دائماً الى الأعلى على اليمين- سيذهب هكذا الى الأبد.
I mean, it had to. Right? I was in for quite a surprise.
أعني، كان علي ذلك. صحيح؟ كانت مفاجأة لي تماماً.
The dotcom, ironically called Snowball,
شركة الدوت كوم، ببلاهة تسمى كرة الثلج،
was the very last consumer web company to go public
كانت أخر شركة مستهلكي الشبكة تذهب للإكتتاب العام
the next month before NASDAQ exploded, and I entered 18 months of business hell.
الشهر التالي قبل إنفجار ناسداك، وبعدها دخلت في 18 شهراً من جحيم الأعمال.
I watched everything that I'd built crumbling,
رأيت -- شاهدت كل شئ بنيته ينهار.
and it looked like all this stuff was going to die
وبدى لي أن كل هذه الأشياء ستموت
and 15 years work would have come for nothing.
وحصيلة 15 عاماً من العمل ستكون لا شئ.
And it was gut wrenching.
وكان عسراً للقناة الهضمية.
It took eight years of blood, sweat and tears to reach 350 employees,
الأولى أستغرقت ثمانية أعوام من الدماء، دموع وفرح لنصل الى 350 موظفاً--
something which I was very proud of in the business.
شئ كنت فخوراً به جداً في أعمالي.
February 2001 -- in one day we laid off 350 people,
فبراير 2001. في يوم واحد سرّحنا 350 شخصاً،
and before the bloodshed was finished, 1,000 people had lost their jobs
وقبل أن تنتهي أحداث العنف، فقد 1000 شخص وظائفهم من--
from my companies. I felt sick.
من شركاتي. أحسست بالاعياء.
I watched my own net worth falling
شاهدت مجموعتي تتساقط
by about a million dollars a day, every day, for 18 months.
بحوالي مليون دولار كل يوم، يومياً، لمدة 18 شهراً.
And worse than that, far worse than that,
و، أسوأ من ذلك، أسوأ من ذلك بكثير،
my sense of self-worth was kind of evaporating.
منظري لتقديري الذاتي نوعاً ما تبخّر.
I was going around with this big sign on my forehead: "LOSER."
كنت أدور في الجوار مع علامة كبيرة في جبهتي: " فاشل."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I think what disgusts me more than anything, looking back,
وأعتقد أن ما جعلني أشمئز أكثر من أي شئ، سابق له،
is how the hell did I let my personal happiness
هو كيف أنني سمحت لسعادتي الشخصية
get so tied up with this business thing?
مرتبطة بشدة مع الأعمال؟
Well, in the end, we were able to save Future and Snowball,
حسناً، في النهاية، أستطعنا إنقاذ المستقبل وكرة الثلج
but I was, at that point, ready to move on.
لكن، كنت في تلك النقطة، جاهز للمضي قدماً،
And to cut a long story short, here's where I came to.
ولإختصار الحكاية الطويلة، هذا ما توصلت اليه.
And the reason I'm telling this story is that I believe, from many conversations,
وسبب إخباري لكم هذه القصة أنني أعتقد، من العديد من النقاشات،
that a lot of people in this room have been through a similar kind of rollercoaster --
أن الكثير من الناس في هذه القاعة مرّوا على نوع مشابه من العجلة الدوارة--
emotional rollercoaster -- in the last couple years.
عجلة العواطف الدوارة-- في السنوات القليلة الماضية.
This has been a big, big transition time,
كان هذا وقت إنتقالي كبير، كبير جداً،
and I believe that this conference can play a big part for all of us
وأعتقد أن هذا المؤتمر يمكن أن يلعب دوراً لنا جميعاً
in taking us forward to the next stage to whatever's next.
في أخذنا الى الأمام الى المرحلة التالية، مهما كان التالي.
The theme next year is re-birth.
الشعار للسنة القادمة هو إعادة الولادة
It was at the same TED two years ago
نفس الشعار كان في تيد قبل عامين
when Richard and I reached an agreement on the future of TED.
عندما توصلنا أنا وريتشارد الى إتفاق حول مستقبل تيد.
And at about the same time, and I think partly because of that,
وحوالي نفس الوقت، وأعتقد جزئياً بسبب ذلك،
I started doing something that I'd forgotten about in my business focus:
بدأت في عمل شئ أعتقد أنني نسيته في أعمالي.
I started to read again.
بدأت القرأة مجدداً.
And I discovered that while I'd been busy playing business games,
وأكتشفت أنني بينما كنت مشغولاً بألعاب الأعمال،
there'd been this incredible revolution in so many areas of interest:
كانت هناك ثورة حاصلة في العديد من المجالات--
cosmology to psychology to evolutionary psychology to anthropology
علم الكون ، علم النفس ، وعلم النفس النشوئي ، الى علم الإنسان ،
to ... all this stuff had changed.
الى-- تعلمون، كل هذه الأشياء تغيرت.
And the way in which you could think about us as a species
والطريقة التي يمكنك عبرها التفكير فينا ككائنات،
and us as a planet had just changed so much, and it was incredibly exciting.
ونحن ككوكب تغيرنا كثيراً، وكان كل شئ مدهش بشدة.
And what was really most exciting --
والشئ الأكثر إثارة،
and I think Richard Wurman discovered this at least 20 years before I did --
وأعتقد أن ريتشارد يورمان أكتشف هذا على الأقل 20 عاماً قبلي،
was that all this stuff is connected.
كان أن كل هذه الأشياء متصلة.
It's connected; it all hooks into each other.
أنها متصلة. جميعها مترابطة مع بعضها البعض.
We talk about this a lot,
نتحدث عن هذا كثيراً،
and I thought about trying to give an example of this. So, just one example:
وفكّرت في محاولة تقديم أمثلة لهذا، فقط مثال واحد.
Madame de Gaulle, the wife of the French president,
مدام دي قاوللي، زوجة الرئيس الفرنسي،
was famously asked once, "What do you most desire?"
سألت مرة ، " ما هو أكثر شئ ترغبين فيه؟"
And she answered, "A penis."
وكان جوابها " قضيباً."
And when you think about it, it's very true:
وحينما تفكّر في الأمر، أنه حقيقي.
what we all most desire is a penis --
ما يريده معظمهن هو القضبان.
or "happiness" as we say in English.
أو، تعرفون، "السعادة," كما نقول في الإنجليزية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And something ... good luck with that one in the Japanese translation room.
وشئ -- حسناً، حظاً سعيداً مع ذلك الشئ في غرفة الترجمة اليابانية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But something as basic as happiness,
لكن شيئاً أساسياً مثل السعادة،
which 20 years ago would have been just something for discussion
الذي كان قبل 20 عاماً مثل شئ للنقاش
in the church or mosque or synagogue,
في الكنيسة أو المسجد أو المعبد،
today it turns out that there's dozens of TED-like questions
أصبح اليوم هناك الكثير من الأسئلة المشابهة في أحاديث تيد
that you can ask about it, which are really interesting.
التي يمكنك السؤال عنها وهي مثيرة حقاً.
You can ask about what causes it biochemically:
يمكنك التساؤل عن مسببات السعادة في الكيمياء الحيوية.
neuroscience, serotonin, all that stuff.
علم الأعصاب، والسيروتونين ، وكل الأشياء.
You can ask what are the psychological causes of it:
يمكن السؤال عن مسبباتها النفسية؟
nature? Nurture? Current circumstance?
الطبيعة، الرعاية، الأحوال الحالية؟
Turns out that the research done on that is absolutely mind-blowing.
ويتبين أن البحوث قطعت شوطاً في هذا تعصف بالعقل تماماً.
You can view it as a computing problem, an artificial intelligence problem:
يمكنك إستطلاعها كمسألة حواسيب، مسألة ذكاء إصطناعي.
do you need to incorporate
لماذا-- نحتاج للتعاون
some sort of analog of happiness into a computer brain to make it work properly?
نوعا ما من تماثل السعادة داخل حاسوب العقل لتجعله يعمل صحيحاً؟
You can view it in sort of geopolitical terms
يمكنك إستطلاعها كنوع من المصطلحات الجغرافية
and say, why is it that a billion people on this planet
ونقول، لماذا بليون شخص على هذا الكوكب
are so desperately needy that they have no possibility of happiness,
فقراء ومحتاجين بشدة بحيث لا فرصة لديهم للسعادة،
and whereas almost all the rest of them,
وبينما تقريباً معظمهم،
regardless of how much money they have -- whether it's two dollars a day or whatever --
غض النظر عن كم من المال لديهم، سواء كانت دولارين يومياً أو غيره،
are almost equally happy on average?
معظمهم سعداء في المتوسط؟
Or you can view it as an evolutionary psychology kind of thing:
أو يمكنك اعتبار هذا نشوئية لنوع من علم النفس.
did our genes invent this as a kind of trick
لماذا يحدث-- هل أخترعت جيناتنا هذا كنوع من الخداع
to get us to behave in certain ways? The ant's brain, parasitized,
لجعلنا نتصرف بطرق محددة؟ نمل الدماغ، التطفل،
to make us behave in certain ways so that our genes would propagate?
لجعلنا نتصرف بطرق محددة بحيث تتكاثر جيناتنا؟
Are we the victims of a mass delusion?
هل نحن ضحية لوهم جماعي؟
And so on, and so on.
وهكذا دواليك.
To understand even something as important to us as happiness,
كفهم شئ مهم بالنسبة لنا كالسعادة،
you kind of have to branch off in all these different directions,
يتوجب عليك التبحر في كل هذه الإتجاهات،
and there's nowhere that I've discovered -- other than TED --
ولا يوجد مكان أكتشفته، غير تيد،
where you can ask that many questions in that many different directions.
حيث يمكنني طرح العديد من الأسئلة، في عدد من الإتجاهات المختلفة.
And so, it's the profound thing that Richard talks about:
ولذا، فأنه شئ عميق أن تحدث ريتشارد حول:
to understand anything, you just need to understand the little bits;
لفهم أي شئ، يتوجب عليك فهم قليل من القطع.
a little bit about everything that surrounds it.
شئ قليل عن كل شئ يحيط به.
And so, gradually over these three days,
ولذا، تدريجياً وخلال هذه الثلاثة أيام،
you start off kind of trying to figure out,
تبدأ في محاولة معرفة،
"Why am I listening to all this irrelevant stuff?"
لماذا أستمع لكل هذه المواضيع غير المتعلقة بالموضوع؟
And at the end of the four days,
وفي نهاية اليوم الرابع،
your brain is humming and you feel energized, alive and excited,
يبدأ عقلك بالطنين وتحث بالطاقة، الحياة والإثارة،
and it's because all these different bits have been put together.
وذلك لأن كل تلك القطع وُضعت معاً.
It's the total brain experience, we're going to ...
أنها خبرة العقل الكلية، التي ندخل فيها--
it's the mental equivalent of the full body massage.
أنها المعادل العقلي لتدليك كل جسمنا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Every mental organ addressed. It really is.
كل عضو عقلي يتم مخاطبته. حقيقي يحدث.
Enough of the theory, Chris. Tell us what you're actually going to do, all right?
ما يكفي من التنظير، كريس. أخبرنا عن ما ستقوم بفعله على وجه الخصوص، صحيح؟
So, I will. Here's the vision for TED.
حسناً، سأفعل. ها هي الرؤية ل تيد.
Number one: do nothing. This thing ain't broke, so I ain't gonna fix it.
رقم واحد: لا تفعل شئ. هذا الشئ لن يتوقف، لذا لن أقوم بإصلاحه.
Jeff Bezos kindly remarked to me,
جيف بيزوس نبهني بلطف،
"Chris, TED is a really great conference.
"كريس، تيد فعلاً مؤتمر عظيم.
You're going to have to fuck up really badly to make it bad."
يتوجب عليك جهد عظيم من أجل أن تجعله يفشل."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, I gave myself the job title of TED Custodian for a reason,
لذا أعطيت لنفسي مسمى وظيفي هو أمين تيد لسبب،
and I will promise you right here and now
وأعدكم جميعاً الآن وهنا
that the core values that make TED special are not going to be interfered with.
أن جوهر القيم التي جعلت تيد مؤتمراً مميزاً لا يمكن أن تتضارب.
Truth, curiosity, diversity, no selling, no corporate bullshit,
الحقيقة، الفضول، التنوع، عدم البيع أي هراء شركة،
no bandwagoning, no platforms.
لا فرقة، لا منابر.
Just the pursuit of interest, wherever it lies,
مجرد سعي للمصلحة، إينما تكون،
across all the disciplines that are represented here.
عبر كل التخصصات التي تُقدّم هنا.
That's not going to be changed at all.
لن يتغيّر هذا بتاتاً.
Number two: I am going to put together
رقم أثنين: سأقوم بوضع قائمة
an incredible line up of speakers for next year.
لمتحدثين مدهشين للعام القادم.
The time scale on which TED operates is just fantastic
النطاق الزمني الذي يعمل فيه تيد ممتاز للغاية
after coming out of a magazine business with monthly deadlines.
بعد خروجي من شغل المجلة الشهرية مع مواعيد محددة.
There's a year to do this, and already --
هناك عام لفعل هذا وبالفعل،
I hope to show you a bit later --
كما أرجو لعرض القليل لاحقاً،
there's 25 or so terrific speakers signed up for next year.
هناك 25 متحدث رائعين يصطفون للعام القادم.
And I'm getting fantastic help from the community;
وأتلقى دعم ممتاز من المجتمع--
this is just such a great community. And combined, our contacts
هذا مجتمع عظيم ومتحد، إتصالاتنا
reach pretty much everyone who's interesting in the country, if not the planet.
تصل الجميع تقريباً أي مهتم عبر البلاد، اذا لم يكن الكوكب.
It's true.
هذا حقيقي.
Number three: I do want to, if I can, find a way
رقم ثلاثة: أريد فعل، اذا أستطعت، إيجاد طريقة
of extending the TED experience throughout the year a little bit.
لتوسيع تجربة تيد خلال هذه السنة أكثر قليلاً.
And one key way that we're going to do this is to introduce this book club.
ومفتاح الطريق لفعل ذلك أننا سنقوم بذلك عبر تقديم نادي الكتاب.
Books kind of saved me in the last couple years,
كتب مثل التي أنقذتني قبل عدة سنوات،
and that's a gift that I would like to pass on.
وهذه هدية أريد تمريرها،
So, when you sign up for TED2003, every six weeks you'll get a care package
لذا، عندما تقدمون ل تيد 2003، ستتلقون مجموعة رعاية كل ستة أسابيع
with a book or two and a reason why they're linked to TED.
مع كتاب أو كتابين مع تعليل سبب إرتباطهما مع تيد.
They may well be by a TED speaker,
ربما يكونوا كتب لأحد متحدثي تيد
and so we can get the conversation going during the year
وبذا يكون لدينا مناقشات جارية خلال السنة
and come back next year having had the same intellectual, emotional journey.
ونأتي العام المقبل ولدينا نفس الفكر ، والرحلة العاطفية.
I think it will be great.
أعتقد أنها ستكون فكرة عظيمة
And then, fourthly: I want to mention the Sapling Foundation,
وبعد ذلك، رابعاً، أريد ذكر مؤسسة سابلينغ،
which is the new owner of TED.
التي هي المالك الجديد ل تيد.
What Sapling's ownership means is that all of the proceeds of TED
ما يعنيه ملكية سابلينغ ل تيد هو أن كل عائدات تيد
will go towards the causes that Sapling stands for.
ستذهب من أجل الأهداف التي تسعى لها سابلينغ.
And more important, I think, the ideas that are exhibited and realized here
و، الأكثر أهمية، أعتقد، الأفكار التي يتم عرضها وتحقيقها هنا،
are ideas that the foundation can use, because there's fantastic synergy.
هي أفكار تستطيع المؤسسة إستخدامها كأساس لأنها تأزر رائع.
Already, just in the last few days,
بالفعل، فقط خلال أيام قليلة،
we've had so many people talking about stuff that they care about,
تحدث العديد من الناس حول أشياء يهتمون بها،
that they're passionate about, that can make a difference in the world,
وأشياء هم ملهمون بها، يمكنها صنع تغيير في العالم،
and the idea of getting this group of people together --
وفكرة وضع مجموعة من الناس سوياً--
some of the causes that we believe in,
هي بعض الأهداف التي نعتقد فيها،
the money that this conference can raise and the ideas --
الأموال التي يستطيع هذا المؤتمر تجميعها والأفكار--
I really believe that that combination will, over time, make a difference.
أنني أعتقد أن هذا الجمع، مع مرور الوقت، سيحدث فرقاً.
I'm incredibly excited about that.
أنا مُثار بشدة جراء ذلك.
In fact, I don't think, overall, that I've been as excited by anything ever in my life.
في الحقيقة، لا أعتقد، بعد كل شئ، أنني كنت متشوقاً بأي شئ، في كل حياتي.
I'm in this for the long run,
سأكون في هذا العمل على المدى الطويل
and I would be greatly honored and excited
وسأكون مُكرماً بشدة ومتشوق
if you'll come on this journey with me.
اذا جئتم الى هذه الرحلة معي.